Finding Aid for Wallace C. Williams Papers 1958-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wallace C. Williams Papers 1958-1992
Williams, Wallace C., 1921-
1.25 linear ft.
Detroit businessman active in numerous minority business affairs and organizations. Williams was director of the Michigan Division of Minority Business Enterprise within the Michigan Department of Commerce, 1959-1978. Biographical information, correspondence, files relating to his activities on behalf of minority business development, especially with the Minority Technology Council of Michigan; also files relating to involvement with Detroit civic and cultural organizations, and photographs.
0135 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Wallace C. Williams (donor no. 8891 ) in July, 2000.
The collection is open for research.
Wallace C. Williams was born in Kannapolis, North Carolina, in 1921. He attended the Boro-Hall Academy, New York (1946), Pace College, New York (1947-48), Columbia University, New York (1948-50), Detroit Institute of Technology, Detroit (1957-58), and Wayne State University, Detroit (1969-70). Williams holds a B.S. in Business Technology from the Detroit Institute of Technology.
Throughout his life, Williams was involved in a variety of professional activities concerning primarily minority business affairs. Most notable is his career as director of the Michigan Office of Minority Business Enterprise of the Michigan Department of Commerce, from 1959 to 1978. During that time, Williams was employed by the University of Michigan as a consultant and then was later appointed to the position of research associate at the Special Projects Division, Director of Minority Business Programs.
In addition to his work at the Michigan Department of Commerce and the University of Michigan, Williams has served as chairman of the board and president of the Booker T. Washington Business Association, has served as a charter member and vice president of a University-Government-Business Committee that formed the Minority Technology Council of Michigan, Inc. (MTCM), has been a special consultant to the University of Michigan's Economic Development Administration (EDA) Center for Management and Technology Transfer, and has been a representative to the White House Conference on Small Business. Williams has also lectured at the University of Michigan Business School on several occasions under the auspices of Professor Alfred Edwards.
Other organization and activities in which Williams was involved include Detroit East, Inc. Community Mental Health Center, Made in Detroit, Cotillion Club of Detroit, Detroit Renaissance Center Project, Detroit Mayor-Elect Committee, Entrepreneur Training Program, and as Democratic candidate for the Michigan House of Representatives (1978).
The Wallace C. Williams Papers document various professional and personal activities and concerns of Wallace C. Williams, most notably those during his career at the Michigan Department of Commerce, Office of Minority Business Enterprise. The collection is comprised of a wide variety of materials documenting Williams' activities in a number of organizations and occupations concerned primarily with minority business affairs. The collection is divided into four series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Michigan Department of Commerce, Office of Economic Expansion, Minority Business Development; and Miscellaneous/Organizations.
Of particular interest is the Michigan Department of Commerce series which documents Williams' activities during his tenure at the Michigan Department of Commerce, Office of Minority Business Enterprise. The material in that series reflects Williams' activities directly associated with his position in that office, and other projects in which Williams was active.
Subjects:
African American business enterprises--Michigan.; African American business people--Michigan--Detroit.; Business enterprises--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.; Michigan. Division of Minority Business Enterprise.; Minority business enterprises--Michigan.; Minority Technology Council of Michigan.; Williams, Wallace C., 1921-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Conyers, John, 1929-; Engler, John, 1948-; Thomas, Isiah, 1961-; Williams, Wallace C., 1921-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - General (Box 1)
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Statements (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - February-July 1977 (Box 1)
  - August 1977-December 1977 (Box 1)
- Michigan Department of Commerce, Office of Economic Expansion, Minority Business Development
  - Detroit Economic Development Task Force (Box 1)
  - Minority Business Directories and Mailing Lists (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Performing a Public Procurement Inventory (Box 1)
  - Williams Personnel Information (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous/Organizations
  - Booker T. Washington Businessman's Association
    - Archiving BTWBA (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Business and Industrial Assistance Division, University of Michigan Business School (Box 1)
  - Community Development Block Grant (Box 1)
  - Cotillion Club (Box 1)
  - Democratic Candidate, Michigan House of Representatives, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Center for Success Training (Box 1)
  - Detroit East, Inc (Box 1)
  - Inner-City Business Improvement Forum (Box 1)
  - Life Directions (Box 1)
  - Made in Detroit (Box 1)
  - Michigan Employment Security Commission (Williams personnel information) (Box 1)
  - Minority Business Development Program Proposal (Box 1)
  - Minority Technology Council of Michigan
    - Annual Meetings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Final Report, 1984 Draft (Box 1)
    - General Information (Box 1)
    - Grant Agreements (Box 1)
    - National Association of Management and Technical Assistance Centers (Box 1)
    - Parent Organization (Technology Transfer Center) Reports (Box 1)
    - Reports (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan, Office of the Vice-President for Research Diversity Initiative (Box 1)
  - National Business League (Box 2)
  - New Detroit, Inc (Box 2)
  - Save Orchestra Hall, Inc (Box 2)
  - Phi Beta Sigma (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Special Projects Division (Box 2)
  - Upward Bound (Box 2)
  - Urban Financial Corporation (Box 2)
  - W.C. Williams and Associates (Box 2)
  - YMCA 125th Anniversary Celebration "A Salute to Detroit" (Box 2)